Guide to the Shipping Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Shipping collection
1749-1923
MS 543
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.75
3 boxes.
The collection consists of ships' journals, invoices, manifests, lists of crews, clearance papers and other documents relating to shipping, largely from Connecticut ports in the 18th and 19th centuries. There is also a small quantity of papers from Massachusetts, New York and elsewhere.
Existence and Location of Copies
Entire collection, with the exception of Accession 1999-M-116, is also available on microfilm (3 reels, 35mm.) from Gale, a Cengage Company, at gale.com.
Arrangement
Arranged in order of accession, with an index to ships and masters.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of ships' journals, invoices, manifests, lists of crews, clearance papers and other documents relating to shipping, largely from Connecticut ports in the 18th and 19th centuries. There is also a small quantity of papers from Massachusetts, New York and elsewhere.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
The entire collection, with the exception of Accession 1999-M-116, is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 154 instead of the originals.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Latin American Collection Curator,2015.
Armed Forces; Business; Shipping -- Connecticut; Shipping -- Massachusetts; Shipping -- New York (State) -- New York; Connecticut -- Commerce; Latin America; New Haven (Conn.) -- Commerce; Peru -- History -- War of Independence, 1820-1829; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; United States -- History -- War of 1812; Logbooks; Allyn, Gurdon L.; Austin, William; Barker, David; Barnes, RuBun; Burch, Francis; Bushnell, John L.; Fargo, Henry; Gragg, Charles O.; Griffing, David; Griffing, Jasper; Hitchcock, Elihu; Hoadly, Simeon; Johnson, Emery; Joline, William; Loring, Homer; Loutitt, William; Mack, Andrew; Mahony, Daniel Edward; Moulton, Thomas W.; Pardee, Jesse; Pease, D.; Roath, Henry G.; Russel, John; Saltonstall, Dudley, 1738-1796; Sheffield, William; Simpson, E.; Taylor, William C.; Thorndike, Eben A.; Totten, Gilbert, 1760 or 1761-1839; Tyron, Moses; Wheeler, David; Ansell Gibbs (Ship); Barrosa (Ship); Brittania (Brigantine); Congress (Frigate); Connecticut (Ship); Cynthia (Bark); Deacon (Ship); Eleanor (Schooner); Friendship (Ship: 1797-1827); Gandy (Schooner); George (Brig); Hannah (Schooner); Hartford (Ship); Herald (Schooner); Hiram (Brig); Hitta Franklin (Schooner); Hope (Schooner); Huron (Brig); Intrepid (Sloop); Iris (Bark); James (Brig); John H. Trowbridge (Brig); Julius Webb (Schooner); Keziah (Ship); Lackawanna (Ship); Ladona (Schooner); Live Yankee (Ship); Molly (Schooner); Nancy (Schooner); Nathaniel J. Palmer (Schooner); Nathaniel S. Perkins (Bark); Nile (Bark); Paladium (Ship); Panther (Ship); Pennsylvania (Schooner); Salisbury (Brig); Sally (Sloop); Sarah Frances (Schooner); Superb (Schooner); Telegraph (Schooner); Tempest (Bark); Washington (Sloop); William (Brig 1819-1846); York (Schooner)
- Inventory
  - 13 shipping books of the sloop Intrepid [Captain A. Burr?] with passenger lists and itemization of cargo. These seem to have been weekly trips. 1820 Sep - Dec; 1821 Mar. No ports named. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Account book of the ship Paladium of New London kept by Captain Gurdon L. Allyn, 1847-1849, followed by accounts for the bark Iris in account with the same, 1850-1851, on voyages to Patagonia (S.E. coast of Argentina) for a cargo of guano. ** Entries are for outfitting the seamen, ship's supplies, etc. Loose papers laid in extend to 1859 and show that Captain Allyn was connected with other ships including the bark Tempest. In back of volume are recorded births, marriages and deaths of his and his father's families. [Ship Palladium [sic] in the account books of Edward Learned of New London, same period, seems to have been a whaler.] All seem to have some connection with Frink, Chew & Co. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    General note
    **The papers brought together in the Shipping Collection were acquired over a period of many years and have been calendared in order of accession.
  - Journal+ of two trips from New London to the Patagonian coast of Argentina for cargo of guano**, 1849-1850, 1850-1851 the bark Iris.Also journal+ of the bark Nathaniel S. Perkins on a whaling-and sealing cruise for the Indian and Pacific coasts, 1852-1853 kept by Captain Gurdon L. Allyn. Laid in are three letters, 1874-1874, to Captain Allyn, one each from F.H. & W.S. Chappell, Johnson & Co., - and S.T. Morgan. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    **See Manuscripts, Fall 1953, p.54-55, for an account of the commerce in guano.
    +These journals have been filmed. See Hist. Mss. Film 21 and Whaling and Sealing Logs register for full description.
  - Account book, 1857 Dec - 1861 Mar, kept by Captain Eben A. Thorndike of the ship Live Yankee and calling at Melbourne, Hong Kong, New York and other ports. Includes other miscellaneous ship's accounts. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 2 fragments of a journal kept by Captain Gurdon L. Allyn of the bark Tempest on a whaling voyage, 1857. This journal has been filmed. See Hist. Mss Film 21 and Whaling and Sealing Logs register for a full description. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Log book of the sloop Sally, Jasper Griffing, master, [known as the "Old Commodore."] This log kept by Anmi Harrison of Guilford, 1789 May 4 - 1792 Jun 14, is a record of several voyages from Guilford to Newbern, N.C., thence to points in the West Indies and return, stopping to discharge cargo at various points such as New York and Baltimore. The first voyage was May 4 - Aug 13, 1789; the next began Jan 21, 1791, and thereafter voyages continued regularly until June 15, 1792. Cargoes consisted of beef, corn, peas, rice, pork, molasses, naval stores, lumber salt, flax, wine and other items, with an occasional passenger. Bound in old burlap [original?] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Van Schlank, Anthony. Shipping receipt for skins shipped in The Deacon, New York. [n.m.] 12, 1724. Printed form filled in. In poor condition. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Gt. Brit. Sovereigns, etc. 1760-1821 (George III). Letter of Marque and Reprisal for privateering against French and Spanish ships to Dudley Saltonstall [commander of the brigantine Brittania.] April 17, 1762. Signed Joseph Coit, and Jere: Miller, Deputy Registrar. [Joseph Coit was judge of the court of admiralty of the colony of Connecticut.] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous ships' papers, 1795-1854, including cargo manifests, lists of crews, customs statements, passenger accounts and related legal documents of American ships calling at foreign and American ports. 35 items. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Power of attorney to Moses Tyron, of Wethersfield, late commander of ship Connecticut, January 12, 1801. Signed by members of the crew; witnessed by Lyman Law and Isaac Weeden. On verso are additional names, dated New London, January 13, 1801, and Wethersfield, January 23, 1801, notarized by Lyman Law, notary public and John Williams, justice of ye peace. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Jefferson, Thomas, Pres. U.S., 1743-1826 Clearance papers (printed form filled in) for the schooner Nancy, of New Haven (master, Elihu Hitchcock) bound for Martinique from George Town with a cargo of boards, shingles, staves, bacon, rice, tobacco, corn and poultry. Signed by Jefferson and dated, 1806 February 5. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Two documents relating to Massachusetts shipping. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ms certificate for the consignment of merchandise, 1813. In Spanish. Pencilled note: Mass. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Manifest (printed form filled in) for schooner Hitta Franklin bound from New Bedford for New York, 1817 December 30. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Also two unidentified fragments of manifests, and a blue ribbon with the initials C.A. and the dates, 1854-1879. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Journal of a voyage from Norwich to Wilmington, North Carolina, February 26 - Mar 28, 1853 of the schooner Pennsylvania of New Haven, (master, Henry G. Roath). The Pennsylvania took on a cargo of iron bars at Wilmington. No other cargoes specified. In back, the journal of the schooner Superb, of Norwich (Henry Fargo, master) for Apr 30 - July 23, 1855. The Superb made two voyages in this period. Fragment of a journal for the schooner H.W. Gandy, of New Bedford by Henry Fargo for 1856 and 1860. The back of this journal was used for penmanship exercises and contains two stanzas of a poem. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    See also: box 4, folder 16
  - Journal kept by Captain [Henry] Fargo of several coastal voyages.
    - 1. Journal of a trip from New London, Connecticut to Edenton, North Carolina of the schooner Telegraph. The first trip was Apr 9 - May 24, 1858 with cargo of brick down and corn on return. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 2. Journal of trips from Norwich, Connecticut to Philadelphia, Pennsylvania of the schooner Julius Webb. The Julius Webb made several coal trips to Philadelphia, Jul 7 - Sep 3, 1858 bringing coal up. Down cargo not specified. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 3 documents related to Maine shipping.
    - 1. Contract (printed form filled in) between Samuel Butts owner of the schooner Molly, and David Wheeler, master, and with five seamen for the "season in the Bank or other Codfisheries." Signed by the five seamen, dated, 1792 April 21. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 2. Account (electrostatic copy) for the schooner Nathaniel J. Palmer carrying coal between Philadelphia and Portland, 1911 November 17. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 3. Account (electrostatic copy) for the schooner Eleanor carrying coal between Norfolk and Portland., 1915 October 26. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Logs of Ships, 1814-1923 (Arranged chronologically)
    - Ship and Summary of Log
      - York (U.S. schooner) of Boston, Mass. Cmdr. Francis Burch, master. "The journal of the armed schooner, with a crew of one hundred and nine, mounting ten long nines and four twelve pound cornades." On a cruise from Boston in chase of English ships, the York captured four brigs which were sent back to the United States as prizes and two ships, of which one was set afire and one taken as a prize., 1814 June 24 - September 20 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        100 p. folio
      - Panther (Ship) of Boston, Mass. Captain William Austin, commander. Journal kept by Austin on a voyage from Boston "toward the Columbia River." Sailing from Boston, they rounded Cape Horn on July 20, 1820, and put in at Callao for trade on August 13, taking on a cargo of tin, cotton, and a small amount of vicuna wool. There they were caught in a blockade in consequence of the War of Independence, and remained until November 20 when they left in a convoy. The journal reports the events of this period in detail. Arriving at Samanco on Nov 25, 1820, the captain found "that two days before the People of Vepena, a small village 6 Leagues in the interior, had declared in favor of the Patriots and were pursuing the most conducive steps toward revolutionizing the whole country and my own interest not being effected [?] by these events and being a friend to rational Liberty, I could not but congratulate a people who long oppressed have at length attempted to throw off the yoke of foreigners and to govern themselves." (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - They arrived at Paita (Peru) on December 1 where they took on a cargo of cotton and 25 passengers. On the return journey, they rounded the Cape again on January 7, 1821, with their destination Gibralter (Venezuela). The journal breaks off four days after they pass the Island of Fernando de Naronha off the Brazilian coast., 1820 May 5 - 1821 February 21 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        185 p. folio
      - Nile (Bark) of Boston, Mass. Charles O. Gragg, commander. From St. Iagoes [Cuba?] towards Genoa with a cargo of sugar and coffee. The journal begins at St. Iagoes. They arrived in Genoa on May 24, 1838, and left on June 15, returning to Boston by way of Leghorn, and arriving August 31. (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - A second voyage from Boston to Gibralter is also recorded. Journal entries for this voyage run from October 2, 1838 when the ship left Boston. They returned from Gibralter via Alicante and Malaga. The journal is incomplete, the last entry being February 1, 1839., 1838 February 18 - 1839 February 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        74 p. folio. Many pages missing. The journal has been pasted over as a scrap book, and traces of the removed clippings remain.
      - Cynthia(Bark) "Journal of a voyage from Salem to Canton in the Barque Cynthia commanded by Emery Johnson of Salem, begun in 1838 and terminated 1840. Kept by Charles Upton of Salem." The journal, which is incomplete, begins with the departure from Salem and ends on the return voyage from Manila to New York. The entries are almost entirely on weather, wind, the management of the ship, notes on the ship's diet, with occasional reference to passing ships. (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - The volume was later used as a scrapbook. Clippings have been removed, but traces of newsprint and glue are still visible. It was also used as a notebook, possibly by Emory T. Morris of Salem, Mass., ca. 1864 and 1866 and contains writing exercises and ten drawings, two in color on the front board and 8 in pencil at the back., 1838 October 28 - 1840 March 24 (Box 2, Folder 4)
        78p. folio
      - George (Brig) "Journal of a voyage towards San Francisco from Boston in Brig George in 1852. Kept by Thomas Thompson Seward Boston, Mass." This journal is largely devoted to details of wind, weather and sailing records. A brief entry on August 12 when the brig put in at Valpariso records that the writer resigned his commission, but being unable to secure passage in any other ship, continued on the brig to San Francisco as a passenger. The journal ends with an "Abstract Journal" from October 3 to Oct 19, 1852 when the ship was within two degrees of latitude of San Francisco. (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - At the back of the journal are several pages of musical notation, mathematical computations, financial accounts and chronometer readings rated by E. Simpson, Acting Master of the frigate Congress., 1852 March 4 - October 19 (Box 2, Folder 5)
        88 p. folio
      - Journal of Daniel Edward Mahony of Cumberland County [Maine?] Beginning with a brief autobiographical statement, it continues with summary accounts of his voyages as a seaman on cargo ships between 1863 and 1877. The final entries are for his voyage in 1884 [as captain?] on the brig Salisbury to Rio de Janeiro with accounts for the ship. (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Ladona(Schooner) Log of a race under sail from New London to Bermuda, returning partly under sail, partly by motor to Boston. Captain Homer Loring with six others in the ship's company. Writer of journal not identified., 1923 June 12 - June 26 (Box 2, Folder 7)
        32 p. folio
      - Barrosa(ship) Log of the proceedings of His Majesty's ship Barrosafrom the 29th day of October 1812 to the 28th June 1813. The log was kept by Lieutenant Lechmere. l v. (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - The ship (afterwards the Aspinal) served on the coast of North America during the War of 1812. (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Manifests, Lists and other papers relating to Connecticut shipping. (34 documents), 1792-1861 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        See also: box 4, folder 2
      - Manifests, Lists and other papers relating to Connecticut ships. (33 documents), 1799-1845; undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
        See also: box 4, folder 5
      - Report and manifest of the cargo of the brig John H. Trowbridge, J[?] Bishop and T. Dwight, Jr., owners. New Haven [Conn.], Dec 12, 1825; signed by Simeon Hoadley, master. [Printed form filled in; 1 folio sheet] (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Report and manifest of the cargo of the schooner Sarah Frances, John Bradley and Smith Tuttle, owners. Made to the Collector of the District of New Haven. New Haven [Conn.], Dec 8, 1825; signed by David Barker, master. [Printed form filled in; 1 folio sheet]. (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Report and manifest of cargo of the schooner Sarah Frances shipped from St. Eustatius [W.I.?]. [n.p., possibly New Haven, Conn.; n.d.], signed by David Barker, master. [1 folio sheet]. (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - 20 manifests for cargoes of Connecticut ships, chiefly entering or leaving the port of New Haven, 1800-1803 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - l4 manifests of cargoes of Connecticut ships using the port of New Haven, 1800-1803. 1 manifest 1852 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - 35 manifests, lists and other papers relating to Connecticut ships, 1800-1882 (Box 4, Folder 3)
        See also: Box 3, folder 2.
      - 9 documents relating to New York ships, 1818-1851 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - 4 documents relating to Connecticut ships, 1799; 1803; 1805 (Box 4, Folder 5)
        See also: Box 3, folder 3.
      - Business papers chiefly relating to Captain Gilbert Totten, 1792-1799, with a lease for a pew rental in Trinity Church, New Haven, 1816. Also a folder on the death of Captain William Louttit, listing his effects (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Certificate of David Gelston, Collector of the Port of New York, concerning Curtis Chatfield, seaman. (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Receipt of Peter Totten, U.S. Vice-Counsul at St. Croix, for the register of the brig James, Andrew Mack, master, 1810 February 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Acknowledgment by James Holmes, U.S. Consul in Belfast, of testimony of officers of the ship Keziah, 1810 May 4 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - 3 papers, 1802-1803, of the brig Huron of Guilford, David Griffing, master. (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Miscellaneous papers relating to marine legal cases of Essex, Conn. (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Miscellaneous papers relating to New Haven shipping. Includes passenger and crew lists and ships' licenses. (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Statement to the effect that William Hersey [?] and Simeon Wackley, debtors, shipped on board the schooner Hannah (RuBun [sic]] Barnes, master) bound for the West Indies. Dated New London, May 2 1796 and Baltimore, 1796 July 2 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Atwater, Jeremiah Mix, 1767-1832. Y. 1785. Entry of pickled fish, intended to be exported for the benefit of bounty by Jeremiah M. Atwater in the schooner Herald, whereof Jesse Pardee is master, bound for St. Bartholomews. Port of New Haven, 1816 May 24 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Ship's passage paper issued to Captain D. Pease of ship Ansell Gibbs. New Bedford, Dec 7, 1835. Signed by Andrew Jackson, Pres. U.S., Printed form filled in. (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Connecticut shipping papers, largely Middletown and Wethersfield, 1769-1800 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Connecticut shipping papers, largely ships from Middletown in trade with the West Indies, 1801-1803 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Invoices for duties paid on goods imported from the West Indies, mostly from Middletown, 1804, and other shipping papers. (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Shipping papers and invoices, largely for ships coming from the West Indies to the port of Middletown, 1805, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Miscellaneous shipping papers, including an estimate for building an engine, 1823, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Manifests for cargo for ships from New Haven and Boston, 1749, 1800-1807 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - License issued by the Port of New Haven for the sloop Washington to carry on "the coasting trade for one year,", 1809 January 13. (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Judgment by the court in Antigua confiscating the brig Hiram, as a "lawful Prize to the King… the said brig Hiram … having been captured after His Majesty's Order bearing date the thirteenth day of October 1812 by the said private armed Sloop Eliza Pratt…, 1813 February 23 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Journal. "Remarks on the schooner Superb…" William Joline, master and later William C. Taylor, master. Daily entries Sep 3, 1845 - Sep 30, 1846. The Superb was a coastwise freighter from Richmond, [Pa.] carrying cargoes of coal to points along the Atlantic with return cargoes from various points. (See also Box 1 folder 13 for other entries for the Superb.] (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - Ship's clearance papers (printed form filled in) issued to Thomas W. Moulton, commander of the ship Friendship, Bath, Aug 17, 1795. Signed by George Washington, Edward Randolph, countersigned by William Webb. (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - Ship's clearance papers (printed form filled in) issued to John L. Bushwell, at New London, Dec 3, 1800, master and commander of the schooner Hope, giving registration, destination etc. Signed by John Adams, Pres. U.S., J. Marshall, Secretary of State and countersigned by Jed. Huntington (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - [Both of the above documents are printed forms with parallel columns of French, Spanish, English and Dutch; names, dates and other particulars supplied in manuscript.]
      - Russel, John, master of the sloop Scrub. Contract with seamen for voyage from Middletown to Barbadoes and Martinico and back to Middletown, 1796 Middletown. Printed form filled in and signed by master and seamen. (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - List of persons composing the crew of the brig William of New Haven (William Sheffield, master) bound for the West Indies, giving their place of birth, residence and "description of their persons." Including one black man, Henry Hart of New Haven., 1824 March 26 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Additional Material, Accession 1999-M-116
  Scope and Contents
  This addition to the Shipping Collection has not been microfilmed.
  - Logbooks [arranged chronologically]
    - Hartford (Ship) [kept by cadet/midshipman, H. O. Dunn, U.S. Navy, describes ports visited, foreign ships, and shipboard routine on voyage along coast of Uruguay and Brazil], 1878 May - 1879 March (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Lackawanna (Ship) [kept by midshipman, John A Kimball, U.S. Navy: describes ports visited;, foreign ships and armaments; and shipboard routine on voyage along western coast of South America], 1881-1883 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, 1898-1899; Accession 2015-M-079
  Includes the ship's log from the U.S.S. Resolute.
  - Ship's log of the U.S.S. Resolute, 1898-1899 (Box 1)